{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "During a conflict in this region, one commander was baited into aiding the Aedui and was promptly defeated at the battle of Gergovia. The Arverni’s resistance in this region broke after an enemy used the tactics of circumvallation and contravallation at the siege of Alesia. This region was divided into Cisalpine and Transalpine sectors and was conquered by Julius Caesar in 50 BC. Vercingetorix ruled in, for ten points, what Roman province in modern-day France?",
      "answer": "Gaul"
    },
    {
      "question": "For their opposition to one of these laws in 2011, Kansas Secretary of State Kris Kobach called the ACLU “communists” in 2016. A Loyola law study found 31 cases “out of a billion” where these laws would have applied. In July 2016, one of these laws in North Carolina was struck down because it was targeting African-Americans with “surgical precision.” For ten points, name these laws that aim to prevent fraudulent behavior at the voting booth.",
      "answer": [
        "voter ID laws",
        "descriptions of laws that require voters to provide any type of personal identification"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man blamed stray American searchlights for providing vision for his enemy’s guns at Agua Prieta. This post-Madero head of the Divisi´on del Norte worked with Emiliano Zapata to overthrow Venustiano Carranza. George Patton was among the leaders of a force sent to capture this man following his cross-border raid on Columbus, New Mexico. “Blackjack” Pershing failed to kill, for ten points, what general of the Mexican revolution?",
      "answer": "Francisco “Pancho” Villa"
    },
    {
      "question": "An author from this country described spending seventeen months in a waiting line outside her son’s prison in her poem Requiem. Parasha dies during a flood in this country, causing the man who loved her to descend into madness in a poem named after an equestrian statue. For ten points, name this setting of “The Bronze Horseman,” the home country of poet Anna Akhmatova and the author of the verse novel Eugene Onegin, Alexander Pushkin.",
      "answer": [
        "Russia",
        "Soviet Union",
        "USSR",
        "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
        "CCCP",
        "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The downtown of one city in this state was flooded in 1913 by the Great Miami River. A 1995 accord reached in this state ended the war in Bosnia-Herzegovina. Another river in this state caught fire several times, most famously in 1969. The northeastern portion of this state, once claimed by Connecticut as the Western Reserve, is home to the Cuyahoga River. For ten points, name this midwestern state, home to Dayton, Columbus, and Cleveland.",
      "answer": "Ohio"
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure’s body was found in the Tallahatchie River, weighed down by a heavy fan. Jet published images of this figure’s funeral, at which his mother insisted on an open casket. After an all-white jury acquitted J.W. Milam and Roy Bryant of murdering this figure, they freely admitted their guilt in an interview with Look magazine. For ten points, name this 14-year-old from Chicago who was murdered in Mississippi in 1955.",
      "answer": "Emmett Till"
    },
    {
      "question": "One ruler with name was the subject of the “Royal Question” and was forced to abdicate by Jean Duvieusart’s government. Otto of Wittelsbach became King of Greece when another ruler of this name rejected that position. The Casement Report details atrocities that occurred under another ruler of this name, who used the Force Publique [puh-BLEEK] to enforce rubber quotas for workers in the Congo. For ten points, give this name shared by three Belgian Kings.",
      "answer": [
        "L´eopold",
        "any/all of L´eopold I, II,",
        "III"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Kuttabul was sunk in a harbor in this country by three raiding midget submarines. A commander of this country’s forces, Selwyn Porter, oversaw a series of defensive retreats in the Kokoda Track campaign. During World War II, this country was led by John Curtin and Robert Menzies. The Battle of Coral Sea effectively ended Japanese plans to isolate and invade this country. For ten points, name this Allied country that endured assaults on its harbors of Darwin and Sydney.",
      "answer": "Australia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Four children of the More family were boarded onto this ship after their mother was embroiled in an adultery scandal involving Jakob Blakeway. Christopher Jones was the captain of this ship, which was originally intended to be accompanied on an ocean crossing by the Speedwell. The journals of William Bradford preserve a governing document or compact named for this ship. For ten points, name this ship that established the Plymouth Colony after landing at Cape Cod.",
      "answer": "Mayflower"
    },
    {
      "question": "In order to perform this action, numerous U.S. Presidents have joined the Burning Tree Club in Bethesda, Maryland. In April 1961, John F. Kennedy gave a Secret Service agent a head injury by performing this action badly. After repeatedly poorly performing this action, Dwight Eisenhower demanded the removal of a tall pine tree at Augusta National. For ten points, name this common athletic activity for U.S. Presidents, especially Eisenhower, who installed the White House putting green.",
      "answer": [
        "golfing",
        "anything related to golf, including more specific responses, like swinging a golf club, teeing off, etc."
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This kingdom’s first ruler was recognized by the papal bull Manifestis Probatum. This country is part of the oldest alliance still in effect, as it allied with England in 1373. A noble from this country created a school in Sagres and was head of the Order of Christ. It was ruled by the House of Braganza, and Henry the Navigator was part of its House of Aviz. For ten points, name this country that sponsored the first expeditions to India, which brought spices to its capital of Lisbon.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Portugal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Order of Christ in Portugal grew out of the remnants of this crusading order. Clement V disbanded this order after Philip IV nearly destroyed it, and it feuded with the Knights Hospitaller.",
        "answer": "Knights Templar"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An expedition to this country ended in failure after the Battle of Verti´eres [vair-tee-air] and thousands of deaths to yellow fever. A civil war in this country called the War of the Knives ended with the exile of Andr´e Rigaud. This country’s constitution declared its Governor-General for Life to be its revolutionary leader Toussaint L’Ouverture. For ten points, name this French colony, the site of the only slave rebellion to successfully create a free state, found on the island of Hispaniola.",
        "answer": "Haiti"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Haiti became an empire after this man, L’Ouverture’s successor and lieutenant, declared himself emperor. He ordered an 1804 massacre of the white population that terrified the American South.",
        "answer": "Jean-Jacques Dessalines"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, Dudley Field Malone claimed that there is no such thing as “a duel with the truth.” The veracity of the Book of Genesis was questioned in this event, which responded to a violation of the Butler Act. The defense in this trial was led by Clarence Darrow, while the prosecutor was William Jennings Bryan. For ten points, name this 1925 Tennessee court case focusing on a high school teacher who illegally taught evolution.",
        "answer": [
          "Scopes Monkey Trial",
          "State of Tennessee v. Scopes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Scopes trial inspired Jerome Lawrence and Robert Edwin Lee to write this 1955 play. Like Arthur Miller’s The Crucible, this play served as an allegory for the ongoing Red Scare.",
        "answer": "Inherit the Wind"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Lawrence Alma-Tadema painted a creator of this building showing its friezes to his friends. Entasis is used to give the appearance of straightness to this building’s Doric columns. Reliefs of centaurs fighting the Lapiths were among the sculptures removed from this building by the Earl of Elgin in the 19th century. The Delian League’s treasury was sacked to pay for the construction of, for ten points, what temple on the Athenian acropolis?",
        "answer": "The Parthenon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alma-Tadema depicted this Athenian showing off his work on the Parthenon’s friezes. The Athena Parthenos, as well as the giant statue of Zeus at Olympia, were designed by this sculptor.",
        "answer": "Phidias"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The acceptance of these legal items is governed by the “mailbox” rule. Severability clauses influence how eager courts are to amend these documents. A promissory estoppel may be granted by a court to remedy instances when these legal documents are violated. The “right to [these]” was enshrined by the Supreme Court during the Lochner Era. These documents typically consist of an offer, acceptance, intention, and consideration. For ten points, name these legal documents which establish legal duties between private individuals.",
        "answer": "contracts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lochner Era of “liberty of contract” was ended by a case involving the West Coast one of these institutions v. Parrish. In 1964, a similar institution called the Heart of Atlanta was denied the right to refuse service to African-Americans.",
        "answer": [
          "hotels",
          "motels"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In response to this event, laywer Ludovic Trarieux [trair-you] created the Human Rights League. A bordereau central to this event was addressed to Max von Schwartzkoppen, the German military attach´e, promising state secrets. After the acquittal of this scandal’s real culprit, Ferdinand Esterhazy, Emile Zola attacked Felix Faure’s government with the open letter J’accuse. For ten points, name this scandal in which the French government wrongly imprisoned a Jewish artillery officer.",
        "answer": [
          "Dreyfus Affair",
          "equivalents for affair, like scandal"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dreyfus was imprisoned at the penal colony of Devil’s Island, located in this overseas French d´epartment. It is the site of most French rocket launches.",
        "answer": "French Guiana"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state’s Halifax Resolves was the first official colonial action calling for independence. The northern half of this state was also known as the Granville district before the Revolutionary War. The construction of Tryon Palace led to the Battle of Alamance in this state in 1771, where the War of the Regulation took place. Virginia Dare, the first English baby born in the Americas, disappeared in this state’s “Lost Colony” of Roanoke. For ten points, name this state whose capital is named for Sir Walter Raleigh.",
        "answer": "North Carolina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lost Colony at Roanoke left behind few clues to their disappearance; the biggest clue was the carving of this word into wood in the abandoned fort.",
        "answer": "CROATOAN"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The largest city in this region hosts a yearly ice sculpture festival and was once home to the Jurchens. The “outer” portion of this region, beyond the Amur and Ussuri Rivers, was ceded to Russia in a pair of Unequal Treaties. Harbin is the largest city of this region, where the Mukden Incident was used by Japan to establish the puppet state of Manchukuo. The Qing Dynasty was founded by people from, for ten points, what region in the northeast of China?",
        "answer": [
          "Manchuria",
          "Manchukuo after “Mukden” is said and before it itself is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This river, the site of the largest naval battle in the First Sino-Japanese War, is Manchu for “the boundary between two countries” and marks the northern border of North Korea.",
        "answer": "Yalu River"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American Nobel Peace Prize Winners",
      "prompt": "Given the year and a clue, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "2009: then-recently elected U.S. President.",
          "answer": "Barack Obama"
        },
        {
          "question": "2002: former American President, philanthropist, and activist with Habitat for Humanity.",
          "answer": "James Earl “Jimmy” Carter"
        },
        {
          "question": "1964: American minister and civil rights activist who was assassinated in Memphis in 1968.",
          "answer": "Dr. Martin Luther King Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "1906: President who became the first American to win the Peace Prize.",
          "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "2007: former U.S. Vice President for his climate change advocacy.",
          "answer": "Al Gore"
        },
        {
          "question": "1931: American suffragette and reformer who co-founded Hull House.",
          "answer": "Jane Addams"
        },
        {
          "question": "1929: American statesman who co-wrote a pact denouncing war with 1926’s co-winner, Aristide Briand.",
          "answer": "Frank Kellogg"
        },
        {
          "question": "1925: American Vice President who worked on a World War I reparations plan.",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Dawes",
            "Dawes Plan"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The British Labour Party",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Legislative body, divided into the Houses of Commons and Lords, in which Labour has 231 members.",
          "answer": "Parliament of the United Kingdom"
        },
        {
          "question": "Side of the political spectrum to which Labour belongs. The term originated with the Jacobins and refers to more liberal policies.",
          "answer": "the political left"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organizations that allowed workers to collectively bargain, an early source of Labour political support.",
          "answer": [
            "trade unions",
            "labor unions"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Current leader of the Labour Party, an outspoken socialist who succeded Ed Miliband.",
          "answer": "Jeremy Corbyn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Moderate leader of the “New Labour” movement who was Prime Minister from 1997 to 2007.",
          "answer": "Tony Blair"
        },
        {
          "question": "Third party that joined with Labour to form several governments; its modern form entered a coalition with the Conservatives under Nick Clegg.",
          "answer": [
            "Liberal Party or the Liberal Democrats",
            "LibDems"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Labour Prime Minister who succeeded Churchill and introduced the National Health Service.",
          "answer": "Clement Attlee"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Labour Prime Minister, negatively affected by the Zinoviev letter.",
          "answer": "Ramsay MacDonald"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Republic of China",
      "prompt": "Name...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Its island home, off the coast of mainland China.",
          "answer": "Taiwan"
        },
        {
          "question": "The country it fought against after the Marco Polo Bridge Incident. Its soldiers committed the Rape of Nanking.",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "The founder of the Republic of China, called the “Father of the Nation.”",
          "answer": "Sun Yat-sen"
        },
        {
          "question": "The leader of the Northern Expedition and head of the Republic during the Chinese Civil War.",
          "answer": "Chiang Kai-shek or Jiang Jieshi"
        },
        {
          "question": "The political party that dominates the ROC’s politics and holds a territorial claim over mainland China.",
          "answer": [
            "Kuomintang or KMT",
            "Guomindang",
            "Nationalist Party of China"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The organ of the United Nations in which the Republic maintained a permanent seat and veto power until 1971.",
          "answer": "United Nations Security Council or UNSC"
        },
        {
          "question": "The 1911 revolution that brought the Republic to power, overthrowing Puyi.",
          "answer": "Xinhai Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "The American fighter squadron commanded by Claire Chennault that fought with the Republic during World War II.",
          "answer": "Flying Tigers or the 1st American Volunteer Group"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, the Khalq and Parcham factions of the People’s Democratic Party split in the lead-up to the PDP’s revolt against Mohammed Daoud Khan; Khan was then assassinated by Khalqist military forces, sparking the Saur Revolution in (20 pts)",
        "1978. In 1996, Ahmad Shah Massoud co-founded the Northern Alliance to oppose a majority-Pashtun military government; that alliance eventually dissolved after Hamid Karzai became its president, supported by the U.S. after its (10 pts)",
        "2001 invasion. For ten points, name this country, once ruled by the Taliban from its capital of Kabul."
      ],
      "answer": "Islamic Republic of Afghanistan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle took place near Horns Reef thanks to Room 40’s success in decoding enemy messages. In this battle, several ships were destroyed during the Run to the South before a reversal and a Run to the North. In this battle, David Beatty’s battlecruisers took heavy losses and were forced to withdraw until John (20 pts)",
        "Jellicoe’s main fleet arrived. This battle occurred despite the fleet-in-being strategy of the German High Seas Fleet, which tried to avoid action against the superior (10 pts)",
        "British Grand Fleet. For ten points, name this major 1916 battle, the largest naval battle of World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Jutland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The X-15 research aircraft used liquid oxygen and this substance as rocket propellant. The Ostwald process converts this compound into nitric acid. In (20 pts)",
        "1909, a method of producing this substance using an osmium or iron catalyst and components from the air was developed by (10 pts)",
        "Haber and Bosch, providing saltpeter-starved Germany with explosive material during World War I. For ten points, name this gas with chemical formula NH , important in cleaning 3 supplies and fertilizer."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "anhydrous ammonia",
        "NH before mentioned 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) AP reporter Robert Geiger first coined this term after witnessing Black Sunday. The SCS was created by Harold Ickes to deal with the aftermath of this event. A shelterbelt of over 200 million (20 pts)",
        "trees was planted by the CCC in the wake of this event. Dorothea Lange’s “Migrant Mother” shows one of millions of displaced (10 pts)",
        "“Okies” fleeing to California for work during this event. For ten points, name this widespread agricultural disaster that plagued the Great Plains during the Great Depression."
      ],
      "answer": "Dust Bowl do not"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote that he had once visited the “third heaven” and seen “things man is not permitted to tell.” Though he longed to travel to Bithynia, a vision inspired a visit to Macedonia instead. This man, who miraculously survived a (20 pts)",
        "snakebite in Malta following a shipwreck, approved of the martyrdom of Stephen before falling to the ground and becoming blind in a (10 pts)",
        "conversion experience on the road to Damascus. For ten points, name this early Christian apostle and author of much of the New Testament."
      ],
      "answer": "Paul or Saul of Tarsus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The theme of this piece’s final movement was used for its composer’s Opus 35 Variations and Fugue. In its first movement, a solo horn enters with the recapitulation four measures early. On the day of JFK’s assassination, the Boston Symphony Orchestra altered its program to play this piece’s second movement, a (20 pts)",
        "funeral march. Its composer dedicated it “to the memory of a great man,” supposedly ripping up the original title page after (10 pts)",
        "Napoleon declared himself Emperor. For ten points, name this symphony by Ludwig van Beethoven."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Beethoven’s Symphony No. 3 in E-flat major or the Eroica Symphony",
        "“symphony” and “Beethoven” are not needed after they are said"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This region was conquered after the Battle of Chuvash Cape and the defeat of Kuchum Khan. Tyumen was the first European settlement in this region. The Stroganov family financed the conquest of this region by a group led by (20 pts)",
        "Yermak, leading to an explosion in the fur trade. This region’s culture was driven by participants in the failed Decembrist revolt, who were (10 pts)",
        "sent here. The port of Vladivostok was selected as the eastern terminus of a railroad that crosses, for ten points, what enormous, desolate eastern region of Russia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Siberia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s treasury secretary, Benjamin Bristow, exposed widescale bribery involving taxes on alcohol. This President was manipulated by James Fisk and Jay Gould in the (20 pts)",
        "“Black Friday” scheme to corner the gold market. During this man’s re-election campaign against Horace Greeley, his opponents railed against his vice president, Schulyer Colfax, and others for taking bribes from a (10 pts)",
        "railroad construction company. For ten points, name this U.S. president whose administration was plagued by the Whiskey Ring and Credit Mobilier [moh-beel-yay] scandals, but whose reputation as a Union general earned him re-election."
      ],
      "answer": "Ulysses S. Grant"
    }
  ]
}